Guide to the J. Dennis Huston Literary Papers, 1964-2016 UA 390
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
J. Dennis Huston Literary Papers
1964-2016
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Huston, J. Dennis
UA 390
5.5 Linear Feet 4 boxes + map drawer
These papers relate to the scholarly and teaching career of J. Dennis Huston. They reflect the courses he taught on the plays of Shakespeare and other British Renaissance dramatists, on detective fiction, and on works constituting the Western humanities tradition. Also included are materials reflecting the administration of Rice University's required Humanities Foundation Course. There are syllabi of Huston courses, student evaluations of these courses, articles written by others about the teaching of writing, varied short texts written by Huston, correspondence, news clippings, photographs, and ephemera.
Biographical / Historical
J. Dennis Huston, the Gladys Louise Fox Professor Emeritus of English at Rice University, was born September 21, 1939. He received his B.A. from Wesleyan University in 1961 and his M.A. (1964) and Ph.D. (1966) from Yale University. In 1966-67 he was an instructor of English at Yale and an Assistant Professor there for the following two years. In 1969 he became an Associate Professor at Rice University and in 1980 was promoted to full professor. His distinguished record of awards for outstanding teaching began in 1975 with the Brown College Teaching Award. The Nicholas Salgo Distinguished Teacher Award was won by Huston that same year and again in 1984. In 1977, 1979, 1981, and 1988 he received a George R. Brown Prize for Excellence in Teaching. The George R. Brown Certificate of Highest Merit followed in 1989, making him ineligible for life for further Brown teaching awards. His outstanding skills as a teacher received nationwide recognition in 1989 when he was chosen Professor of the year by the Carnegie Foundation and the Council for the Advancement and Support of Education.
Huston is the author of "Shakespeare's Comedies of Play" and co-editor of a collection of Renaissance plays. He has recorded video lectures on Shakespeare and on detective fiction for The Teaching Company. When the Rice faculty and administration decided that there should be foundational courses in the humanities, social sciences, and natural sciences required for students contrasting with their majors, Dennis Huston was chosen to be director of the Humanities Foundation Course. From 1978 to 1982 and again from 1992 to 1998 he was a co-master of Rice's Hanszen College, one of the student residence halls on campus. He is a past president of Rice's Beta of Texas chapter of Phi Beta Kappa and has served on the Phi Beta Kappa Alumni Association of Greater Houston's board of directors since 1999.
Scope and Contents
These papers relate to the scholarly and teaching career of J. Dennis Huston. They reflect the courses he taught on the plays of Shakespeare and other British Renaissance dramatists, on detective fiction, and on works constituting the Western humanities tradition. Also included are materials reflecting the administration of Rice University's required Humanities Foundation Course. There are syllabi of Huston courses, student evaluations of these courses, articles written by others about the teaching of writing, varied short texts written by Huston, correspondence, news clippings, photographs, and ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection open for research without restrictions, except for the selected folders in Series V: Personal, which is restricted from all viewing and use until 2050.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was a gift donated by Dr. J. Dennis Huston in 2017.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; 16th- 19th century English literature; English literature -- Early modern, 1500-1700 -- History and criticism; Faculty; Literature
Places
Rice University
- Series I: Notes on Works by Major British Authors
  - Notes on Beowulf (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notes on texts by Chaucer (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Essay on Gawain and the Green Knight (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notes on The Second Shepherd's Play (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes on texts by Edmund Spenser (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Spenser's Faerie Queene (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Faerie Queene Book II (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Essay by Harry Berger, Jr. on Faerie Queene Book III (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes on Faerie Queene Booke III (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notes on Faerie Queene Book IV (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Notes on the Faerie Queene Books V-VI (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes on Elizabethan poetry and Sidney's Defense (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Marlowe's Dr. Faustus (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes on Marlowe's Edward II (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes on Marlowe's Jew of Malta (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Notes on Marlowe's Tamburlaine (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes on Thomas Kyd's Spanish Tragedy (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Notes on Ben Jonson's The Alchemist (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notes on Ben Jonson's Bartholomew Fair (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Notes on Ben Jonson's Volpone (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The Age of Elizabeth (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's All's Well that Ends Well (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Antony and Cleopatra (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's As You Like It 1 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's As You Like It 2 of 2 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Comedy of Errors (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Cymbeline (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Henry IV, Parts I and II (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Julius Caesar (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's King Lear (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Love's Labour's Lost (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Measure for Measure (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's The Merry Wives of Windsor (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Richard II (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Richard III (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Sonnets (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's The Tempest (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Timon of Athens (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Troilus and Cressida (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's Two Gentlemen of Verona (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Notes on Shakespeare's The Winter's Tale (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Jonson vs. Shakespeare (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Notes on Shakespeare in performance (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Notes on Shakespearean comedy (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Notes on Shakespearean tragedy (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Shakespeare's Final View of Women" by D. W. Harding (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Notes on the Dramaturgy of Shakespeare's Romances by Barbara Mowat (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Notes on Psychoanalysis and Shakespeare by Norman Holland (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Text by J. Dennis Huston on teaching Shakespeare's comedies (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Notes on The Duchess of Malfi by John Webster (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Notes on The White Devil by John Webster (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes on the Revenger's Tragedy by Thomas Middleton (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes on The Changeling by Middleton and Rowley (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notes on A King and No King by Beaumont and Fletcher (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes on 'Tis Pity She's a Whore by John Ford (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series II: Notes on texts in the humanities from Greek drama to the 20th century
  - Aeneid Essays (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alberti, On Painting (1435-6) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Aristophanes, The Archanians (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Aristophanes, The Birds (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Aristophanes, The Clouds (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Aristophanes, The Frogs (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Arnold, "Dover Beach" (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Augustine (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Austen, Sense and Sensibility (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bronte, C., Jane Eyre (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bronte, E., Wuthering Heights (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cervantes, Don Quixote (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Cicero (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Collins, Wilkie, The Moonstone (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Conrad, Heart of Darkness (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Cortazar, Julio, Blow Up (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Dante (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Descartes (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dickens, Little Dorrit (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ecclesiastes (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Eliot, T. S. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Euripedes, The Bacchae (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Euripedes, Iphigenia at Aulis (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Exodus (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Fielding, Joseph Andrews (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - French Revolution (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Freud (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Gawain and the Green Knight (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Gospel of Thomas (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Greek Drama (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Hawthorne (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Homer (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Islam (Koran) (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - James, Portrait of a Lady (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Job (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Johnson, Samuel (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Joyce, Ulysses (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Jules and Jim (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Kaiser, Walter, Praisers of Folly (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - King, "Letter from Birmingham City Jail" (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Kuhn, The Structure of Scientific Revolutions (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Lincoln's Gettysburg Address (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Livy (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Luther (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Maimonides (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Maimonides essays (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Malraux, Andre, Man's Fate (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Marcus Aurelius (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Marie of France (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Mark (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Mark, Kebler on (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Marriage of Figaro (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - McCullers, Carson, The Heart is a Lonely Hunter (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Melville (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Millington on Hawthorne (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Montaigne (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Narrative (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Narrative of a Slave Girl (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Nietzsche (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Oresteia (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Parker, Robert (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - St. Paul (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Perpetua (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Philoctetes (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pico (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Pico and Ficino (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Plato, Apology and Crito; Plato and Aristotle (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Plato, Phaedo and Phaedrus (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Plato, The Republic (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Plautus and the miles (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Play (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Prometheus Bound (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Purple Hibiscus (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Revolutions (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Romantic Poetry: selections (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sensibility and society (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Seventh Seal and Bonnie and Clyde (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Stern, Tristram Shandy (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Swift, Gulliver's Travels (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Tacitus (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Thecla (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Thucydides (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - West, Nathaniel, Miss Lonelyhearts (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Wordsworth, William (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Series III: Humanities Foundation Course - administration, syllabi, report
  - Humanities Foundation Course - administration (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Excused from Humanities Foundation Course (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Humanities Foundation Course seminar, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Humanities Foundation Course 101 reader - clean copy, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Humanities Foundation Course - first class (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Humanities Foundation Course 101 and 102 - syllabi (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Humanities Foundation Course 101 - possible Rome readings (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Humanities Foundation Course 101, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Humanities Foundation Course 101 and 102, 2004 - 2005 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Humanities Foundation Course - exam questions (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Humanities Foundation Course - planning materials (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Shirley letter about Humanities Foundation Course (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Humanities Foundation Course - Report (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Series IV: Course Materials - syllabi, evaluations, articles about teaching writing
  - English 100 syllabus (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - English 200 syllabus (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - English 251 and Humanities 101 syllabi (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - English 241 first class (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Humanities 260/360 opening lecture (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Comedy course (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Modern Drama syllabus (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Movie Course (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Pedagogy course (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Pedagogy Seminar (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Public Speaking syllabus (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Shakespeare Lectures (taped) (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Shakespeare syllabus, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Shakespeare on Film syllabus (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - 2015-2016 syllabi (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - ACTER: The Alliance for Creative Theatre, Education and Research (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Holder symposium on writing (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Articles on the study of writing (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Lawyer's on Writing (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Student evaluations of Huston courses, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Series V: Personal
  - Wilbur Cross Medal of Yale University, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - CASE Professor of the Year award, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence about the importance of teaching vs. research at Rice University (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Address for Phi Beta Kappa Ceremony of Initiation, 2004 - 2005 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Talk prepared for DeLange Conference, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Lecture for Leadership Rice, delivered February 1, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - [Restricted] Letter recommending promotion of Robert Egan (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - [Restricted] Letter recommending promotion of James Calderwood (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Summarized student evaluations of Rice faculty (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Book Chapter: "Managing Discussion in Large Classes" from Inspiring Teaching (Anker, 1996) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Review of "Reading Football: How the Popular Press Created and American Spectacle" (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Review of Shakespeare's Sexual Comedy (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Review of William Shakespeare's Records and Images (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Address: Sierra Nevada graduation (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Comment on students work: English 320 final paper (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Review by Cyrus Hoy of Huston's Shakespeare's Comedies of Play (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Newsclippings: CASE Professor of the Year Award, etc. (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence: Teaching Company (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence: Vellacott visit (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Photographs (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Intramural Championship certificates (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Sallyport containing article about Huston (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Series VI: Oversize
  - Large Photograph of Huston in dramatic role (Drawer 35, Folder 8)
  - Poster for staging of The Country Wife with Huston's face illustrate (Drawer 35, Folder 8)